Guide to the George Mason University Office of the President records, 1949-2004
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
George Mason University Office of the President records
1949-2004
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
George Mason University Office of the President
R0019
68 linear feet (131 boxes)
Records in this collection contain memoranda, correspondence, studies, reports, speeches, meeting minutes, calendars, articles and newspaper clippings, publications, scrapbooks, and photographs originating in or directed to the GMU Office of the President.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by George Mason Universtiy.
Historical Information
George Mason University's roots can be traced to the University of Virginia (UVa) Extension Division's Northern Virginia University Center. The Extension Division, under the direction of George B. Zehmer, established UVa's Northern Virginia University Center in September 1949 with John Norville Gibson Finley (1899-1971) as the Center's first director. The Center's administrative offices and "campus," were located on the campus of Washington - Lee High School in Arlington, Virginia. During the Center's beginning years, it offered college-level courses for adults.
By 1956, sensing the public need for a college in Northern Virginia area for recent high school graduates, the Extension Division proposed and created, with the help of the Virginia State Legislature, a new two-year branch college alongside the Northern Virginia Center. The branch was called the University College. Finley was appointed director of the new college, whose administrative office was also located on the campus of Washington - Lee High School. Finley remained director of both schools through the 1950s.
In 1957, the University of Virginia leased the vacant Bailey's Crossroads Elementary School for the University College's temporary site. The building was renovated and outfitted with laboratory equipment and other additions needed to make it ready for college instruction. Meanwhile, UVa sought a more permanent site for the new college. In 1959 the Town of Fairfax donated the tract of land on which the University resides today. Director Finley saw the first buildings completed in late 1963 and early 1964.
Robert H. Reid (1913-1970) was director of George Mason College from 1964-1966. During his tenure, George Mason College moved from Bailey's Crossroads to the new 150 acre campus just outside of Fairfax City. The Virginia General Assembly passed a bill to expand GMC to a four-year degree-granting institution in 1966. Reid resigned in March, 1966 stating that his resignation had been prompted by the failure of the 1966 General Assembly to make George Mason independent of the University of Virginia.
In 1966, Lorin A. Thompson (1902-1999), became the first chancellor of George Mason College, and in 1972, the first president of the newly independent George Mason University. During his seven years, 1966-1973, the student population grew from 840 to more than 4,000; and in 1970 Mason began its first graduate program.
Vergil H. Dykstra (1925-2010), president of George Mason University from 1973 to 1977, described his years at Mason as demanding and difficult, but rewarding. Rapid growth of the University continued as undergraduate and graduate programs were added to the curriculum. He also proposed establishing a law school for the University and expanded academic facilities.
Robert C. Krug (1918-2006) came to George Mason College in 1965. Prior to accepting the presidency, after Vergil Dykstra's resignation in April 1977, Dr. Krug held the positions of Dean of the College, Dean of the Faculty and Graduate School, Provost, and Vice President for Academic Affairs. During his presidency from 1977 to 1978, Krug proved to be an effective lobbyist for funds from Richmond. He also obtained the University's first computers.
George W. Johnson (1928- ), inaugurated president in 1979, guided George Mason University from a small liberal arts college into a major university. In his eighteen years as president, George Mason University acquired doctoral status; establish a law school; instituted thirty-four new programs; created new organizational structures; including six academic institutes, and became a distributed university with campuses in Arlington and Prince William counties. Johnson also instituted the Early Identification Program and the Mason Scholars Program.
Alan G. Merten (1941- ) became the fifth president of George Mason University in July of 1996 and he has announced his retirement for June 2012. During his time as president, Merten has successfully stressed connecting research, teaching, and outreach activities; increasing the positive perception of George Mason; initiating activities with a local impact; and identifying and pursuing bases of financial support.
Scope and Content
The Office of the President records contain material originating in or directed to the GMU Office of the President and used in the University's business. Types of material include memoranda, correspondence, studies, reports, speeches, meeting minutes, calendars, articles and newspaper clippings, publications, scrapbooks, and photographs. Topics and institutions to which these materials pertain include the University of Virginia (as GMU's parent institution), the Northern Virginia Center, University planning and expansion with regard to building and academic programs, the State Council for Higher Education of Virginia (SCHEV), and relations with Virginia government officials.
The collection is divided into seven series based on the president of the University. Exceptions to this scheme are the first two series: Annual Reports and Early History. Many of the annual reports were already grouped together, rather than dividing them by president they became the first series. Annual reports, written by the director or president, from George Mason College (1960-1969) to George Mason University (1971-1980), document the rate of change during George Mason's first twenty years. The reports stop in 1980 due to redundancy of information found in the annually released Factbook.
George Mason did not formally have a president until Chancellor Thompson became President Thompson in 1972. Series two encompasses the early history of George Mason University and includes information on the first directors of the institution - John Norville Gibson Finley and Robert H. Reid most notably. This series is titled Early History, and contains papers dating from 1949-1967 on the beginnings of George Mason as an institution when it was the University of Virginia (UVa) Extension Division's Northern Virginia University Center to the development of George Mason College. Included in the series is correspondence, building plans, reports, meeting notes, proposals, and articles.
In 1966 George Mason College became a four-year degree-granting institution and hired Lorin A. Thompson as chancellor. In 1972 Thompson became the first president of the newly independent George Mason University. Series three Lorin A. Thompson, with documents dating from 1964-1975, includes advisory board minutes, correspondence, faculty meeting minutes, educational planning, financial needs, university policies and procedures, land acquisition and building plans, memoranda, photographs, scrapbooks, and reports.
Series four, Vergil H. Dykstra, with papers dating from 1962 to 1980, focuses on the years Dykstra served as president of George Mason University from 1973 to 1977. This series includes budget reports, a Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) report, State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) papers, building plans, and documents from the University Center in Virginia, Inc.
Series five, Robert C. Krug, focuses on Dr. Krug's tenure as president during 1977-1978. Included in this series is correspondence, memoranda, documents on campus security officers and the 1977 bond referendum.
Series six, George W. Johnson, with materials dating from 1957 to 2004, is the largest series in this collection. George W. Johnson was president from 1979 to 1996 and successfully guided George Mason University from a small liberal arts college into a major university. Included in this series are facilities and education plans for expansion in Arlington and Prince William, articles and notes collected by Johnson, documents on athletics, Board of Visitors meeting minutes, daily calendars, documents on the campus police, correspondence, documents concerning Larry Czarda, correspondence with various state departments, facilities planning papers, the Faculty Senate meeting minutes, Governor's files, documents on Johnson's inauguration, memoranda, Office of the Attorney General correspondence, newsclippings, Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) self-study, speeches, as well as documents from the State Council of Higher Education (SCHEV), University life, and the Washington Research Libraries Consortium (WRLC). Photographs, scrapbooks, and the George Mason stamp are also present in this series.
Alan G. Merten became the fifth president of George Mason University in July of 1996 and he has announced his retirement for June 2012. Series 7, Alan G. Merten, includes documents from 1990-2004. Found within this series are papers concerning university athletics, economic development, partnerships, and conferences, as well as, correspondence and memoranda.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series by president. Each series is arranged alphabetically by subject and then chronologically.
Series 1: Annual Reports, 1960-1980 (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Early History, 1949-1967 (Boxes 3-5)
Series 3: Lorin A. Thompson, 1964-1975 (Boxes 5-22)
Series 4: Vergil H. Dykstra, 1962-1980 (Boxes 23-28)
Series 5: Robert C. Krug, 1977-1978 (Boxes 28-30)
Series 6: George W. Johnson, 1957-2004 (Box 30-106)
Series 7: Alan G. Merten, 1990-2004, (Box 107-131)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds the George Mason University records.
Index Terms
Persons:
Dykstra, Virgil H., 1925-2010.; Johnson, George W., 1928-.; Krug, Robert C., 1918-2006.; Reid, Robert H., 1913-1970.; Thompson, Lorin A., 1902-1999.; Merten, Allan G., 1941-.
Corporate Names:
George Mason University. Office of the President.
Subjects:
Universities and colleges--Administration.
George Mason University Office of the President records
- Series 1: Annual Reports, 1960-1980, (2 boxes)
  Annual reports, written by the director or president, from George Mason College (1960-1969) to George Mason University (1971-1980), document the rate of change during George Mason's first twenty years. The reports stop in 1980 due to redundancy of information found in the annually released Factbook.
  - Annual Report, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Report, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Report, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report after 1980, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Note on why President Johnson ceased issuing annual reports.
- Series 2: Early History, 1949-1967, (2.5 boxes)
  George Mason did not formally have a president until Chancellor Thompson became President Thompson in 1972. Series two encompasses the early history of George Mason University and includes information on the first directors of the institution - John Norville Gibson Finley and Robert H. Reid most notably. This series is titled "Early History", and contains papers dating from 1949-1967 on the beginnings of George Mason as an institution when it was the University of Virginia (UVa) Extension Division's Northern Virginia University Center to the development of George Mason College. Included in the series is correspondence, building plans, reports, meeting notes, proposals, and articles.
  - 7 Days in May, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 7 Days in May 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Administration committees, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Admission reports, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Advisory council, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Commonwealth Of Virginia, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Monthly reports, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Darden, Colgate W. Jr. and J.N.G. Finley, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Dedication, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Dedication Day, November 12, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Equipment (Reid), 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Financial report, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Finley papers correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Finley personal correspondence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Finley talk at Marymount, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Four year college proposal, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - George Mason College expansion requirements, circa 1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gifts to the College, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The honor system of the George Mason College, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Initial planning, 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Institutional analysis: James H. Bash & Reid, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Letter regarding Northern Virginia University Center, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Library building [1 of 2], 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Library building [2 of 2], 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Moyer, David B.: Bursar, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Northern Virginia Center, 1958-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Orientation for faculty and student, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Personnel, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Personnel: Salary ranges and race question, 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Planning, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Planning committee minutes, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Registration data, 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Reid, Robert memo regarding faculty meeting minutes, May 21, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Report of the Dean with respect to the Academic Programs & Faculty of George Mason College, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - State Council Of Higher Education reports, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - State Council Of Higher Education Virginia (SCHEV), University of Virginia, administration, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - State University of New York (SUNY) planning guidelines for facilities, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Statistics: George Mason University College, 1955-1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Student affairs committee, 1960-1966 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - United States Commission On Civil Rights, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - University of Virginia extension division, 1949-1966 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    copies of documents from 1949-1966
  - University of Virginia extension division: Progress report of the Northern Virginia University Center, July 1, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Vaughan, Joseph Lee [Reid], 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Vaughan, Joseph Lee [Reid], 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Vaughan, Joseph L.: Chancellor-Charlottesville [Reid], 1963 -1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Vaughan, Joseph L. [Reid], 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chancellor Joseph L. Vaughan [Reid-Thompson], 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Weekly administrative staff meeting, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series 3: Lorin A. Thompson, 1964-1975, (17.5 boxes)
  In 1966 George Mason College became a four-year degree-granting institution and hired Lorin A. Thompson as chancellor. In 1972 Thompson became the first president of the newly independent George Mason University. Series three "Lorin A. Thompson", covering the years 1964-1975, includes advisory board minutes, correspondence, faculty meeting minutes, educational planning, financial needs, University policies and procedures, land acquisition and building plans, memoranda, photographs, scrapbooks, and reports.
  - A regional University for Northern Virginia: Plan of George Mason College of University of Virginia 1968-1975, related documents, November 29, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - A regional University for Northern Virginia: Plan of George Mason College of University of Virginia 1968-1976, circa 1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Academic appeals, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Academic space assignment, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Ad-Hoc committee, educational policies & guidelines, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Administration job description, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Admissions advisory, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Advisory Board GMC, 1965-1972 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Board agenda, 1969-1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Board: Arundel, Arthur W., 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Board: Bryan, Albert V., 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Board: Campbell, Mrs. Edmund D., 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Advisory Board: Caruthers, Preston C., 1965-1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Advisory Board: General, 1966-1970 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Board: Harrison, B. Powell, 1969-1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Advisory Board: Hazel, John T., 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Advisory Board: Henderson, John O., 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Advisory Board: Hirst, Omer L., 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Advisory Board - Mann, C. Harrison, 1965-1972 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Advisory Board: Parris, Stanford E., 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Advisory Board: Robinson, Clarence J., 1964-1971 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Members of the George Mason College Advisory Board, 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Members of the George Mason College Advisory Board, 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Advisory Board meeting minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Advisory Board meeting minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Advisory Board meeting minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Advisory Board meeting minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Board meeting minutes, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Board meeting minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Board meeting minutes, 1961-1972 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Advisory committee, 1965-1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Advisory committee general file, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Advisory committee general file, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Advisory committee file, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Advisory committee resolutions, 1965-1970 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Advisory committee terms of office, 1964-1972 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Affirmative Action disclosure of information, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Affirmative action executive order 11246, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP): Reports, 1967-1972 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - American Council on Education: Questionnaire, June, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Appointment of Lorin A. Thompson, letter from President Shannon, 24272 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Article on Thompson from the Richmond Times, April 5, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Articles on Washington Metro Area, 1967-1971 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Athletic council, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Blankingship, Hugo Jr., 1966-1973 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Bomb threats, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Bond issue, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Budget Advisory Board tour, May 21, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Certification regulations for teachers, July 1, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Child Care Center [1 of 3], 1970-1973 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Child Care Center [2 of 3], 1970-1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Child Care Center, Dykstra [3 of 3], 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Commencement speeches, 1974-1980 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Committees: General, 1968-1973 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Conference On Higher Education, 26177 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Continuing education, 1968-1974 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Continuing education, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Bylaws of the faculty, circa 1970s (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Governor, 1969-1972 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Law school, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Counselors conference, November 30, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Dedication of Arts & Sciences Building, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Department Chairman, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Department Chairman, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Development plan for George Mason College of the University of Virginia, 24716 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Eastern Shore Branch of University of Virginia, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    Includes photographs
  - Ecumenical Center, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Educational plan Of George Mason College, 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Educational planning for George Mason College, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Educational program: Planning task force, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Enabling Act legislation before General Assembly, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Enrollment statistics, 1966-1974 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Factors influencing the total cost of higher education, March 6, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Faculty dinner, October 1, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Faculty library committee, November 9, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Faculty meeting minutes, 1966-1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Faculty meeting, 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Faculty meeting, 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Senate, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Senate, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Fairfax county council on human relations, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Final day exercises, 1965-1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Financial needs of George Mason College 1970-1972, May 6, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Financial needs of George Mason College 1972-1974, May 24, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Fine arts exhibits, 1969-1972 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Four Acres, 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Freedom and tenure, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Freshman profile, circa 1960s (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - George Mason College Reports to You, 1967-1969 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - George Mason Day, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - George Mason essay contest, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - George Mason University night orientation, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Government executive order 29, 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Governors meeting, 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Graduate appeals, 1970-1973 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    RESTRICTED
  - Graduation appeals committee, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Graduate program: Possible visit from Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, March 29-30, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Graduate students, 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Greenhouse, 1969-1974 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Guidebook of college policies and procedures, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Guidebook of college policies and procedures, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Guidebook of college policies and procedures, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Herndon College, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 5)